<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cloud opened, or, The English heroe by a loyal and impartial pen.</title>
            <author>Loyal and impartial pen.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10261434</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10261434</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33485)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1380:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cloud opened, or, The English heroe by a loyal and impartial pen.</title>
                  <author>Loyal and impartial pen.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Albemarle, George Monck, --  Duke of, 1608-1670.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Cloud Opened; OR, THE Engliſh Heroe.</p>
            <p>By a Loyal and Impartial Pen.</p>
            <q>Quam facile fit caecus dux vitae, &amp; obſcura lux temporum Hiſtoria? Si non amentiae, rarus eſt qui non ineptiae litavit. Unicus ſit qui Deo &amp; veritati obtulit.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed <hi>A. D.</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44746:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44746:2"/>
            <head>The Cloud Opened; OR, THE Engliſh Heroes.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ONogylos</hi> is an Herb worthy of Aſſes, a Lactuce like their Lips, rough and prickly; yet (if Herbaliſts are to be credited) a Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſon. Adulation, though ſmooth as oyl, is no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexipharmick. The tame Beaſt, a Flatterer, is more ſpotted, nor leſs cruel than the Leopard or a Tyger. And with the gayety of a Serpent, the rich ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eſing of an Adders skin hath no unequal Poyſon.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:44746:3"/>
            <p>In the late Tyranny, (when Reaſon ſeem'd the moſt extravagant Freak, and Religion and Loyalty had the repute of ſuch Grand Malignants, as a Plague might be ſuppoſ'd to harbour leſs of Contagion) a Mercenary Trifler would have the Uſurper <hi>Oliver,</hi> an <hi>Olive:</hi> ſure after an happy Revolution, no one can be maſter of more ſenſe than the Clenching Panegyriſt, or Volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Nothing wanted; as much a Stranger to Wit, as to our Nation; his Appetite only ſharpen'd Invention, and the hungry Gut vented Oracles. Where the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture on the Rack, was only taught to patronize Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by making bloudy and blaſphemous Confeſſions; it can be no wonder if <hi>Jotham</hi>'s Parable was forgot by an Exotick Whiffler, where the Olive could yield no Fatneſs to uſurp, and of a Bramble only could come the Fire to deſtroy the Cedars of a Lebanon; ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Land, as, made a Forreſt, was inhabited by wild Beaſts.</p>
            <p>In an Age of Lying Wonders, where a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Antichriſt brought Fire down from Heaven, it could be none of the leaſt of the Miracles, that a <hi>Fiſher</hi> could by <hi>Pagan</hi> Worſhip tranſlate the Brazen Image of a Tyrant into Gold, and make it equal an hundred <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobuſſes</hi> or more pure <hi>Carolines</hi> in value.</p>
            <p>A doubly blind Bard firſt in his own, and (as ſome fancie) ſince by Gods Judgment, would have him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual'd by a <hi>Kingfiſher.</hi> But to have had ſuch a King for his Subject, in whoſe cauſe Chriſtianity might ſeem ingag'd, ſure could not need the temptation of a Bribe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44746:3"/>to him who had not renoune'd the Chriſtian Profeſſion, though pedantically florid, and leſs ſignificant Pens, ſerv'd but as Foils to his <hi>Portraiture</hi> and Sufferings: which were only to be taken from his own Writings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virtue,</hi> which is content with her own reward, and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> which expects no recompence below Heaven, know not how to deſcend to that truckling and ſervile Aſſentation, which has no better. Hieroglyphick, than the moſt impure of Creatures, the ſometimes fawning, and at others, ſnarling and biting Cur.</p>
            <p>The Deceaſed <hi>General</hi> may merit ſome grateful <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cediums,</hi> above ſuch diſmal Ditties as attend upon Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutions, which ſeem more mercileſs than the Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the Law; while the Executioner in metre is more barbarous than the Hangman. The <hi>Muſes</hi> have little to do with <hi>Mars;</hi> yet they muſt not permit a praiſe-worthy perſon to dy, if they have any Faith for their Arch-Prieſt the Prince of Lyricks. It is a Tribute due to Allegiance, to commend him whom a King would honour. Commands (ſtrong as muſtard) may ſeem unneceſſary to make the Nations eyes water into Elegies for his loſs, who was the ſuppoſed Reſtorer of their ſight; the bleſſed Inſtrument of returning a King, who may be truly call'd <hi>The Light of our Eyes.</hi> Who would not melt by a Compaſſion (if obdurate for leſſer loſſes) for the <hi>Muſes Helicon,</hi> what the Poets might call Showers of Tears, might ſeem expedient when it is grown ſo muddy, as it cannot furniſh out ſo much clear wit as can ſprinkle an Herſe. Fooliſh Verſifiers, like
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44746:4"/>to Schiſmatical Pulpiteers, by rackt <hi>Hyperbolees</hi> and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd Allegories, make the moſt ſober Truths diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited; Folly diſpraiſes thoſe ſhe would commend, and diminiſhes Glory, by ſeeking to multiply it.</p>
            <p>Who would not believe that a Fable, which muſt have all the Heathen Gods brought into the Scene for the delivery? He who ariſeth early, and praiſeth his friend aloud, it ſhall be reputed to him for a curſe; if the wiſeſt of men is to be believ'd. That a too early and inconſiderate commendation can irritate Envy and Contradiction, which might have ſlept, if not awak'd by raſh and untimely bauling, may be eaſily now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated from the Diſcourſes of Folly.</p>
            <p>Whether Deſign or Chance renders more famous, is incertain. Hiſtory can furniſh us with a Coward, who by the loſs of his head, grew victorious; by a virtue inherent in the Spurs of Honor, the more gen'rous Beaſt which is intitled to want of brains, tranſporting to noble Atchievements. A defect in the noddle hath render'd not a few ſtrangely ſupereminent, whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling Diſpoſition, like that of an inrag'd Horſe, hath qualified for the ruſhing into a Battle. The Pſalmiſt will have an Horſe a vain thing to ſave a man: to raiſe one to a fair Mount of Honor, ſome can inſtance <hi>H. B.</hi> who for a Knighthood and Lordſhip would cry God-a-mercy to his Beaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Anello</hi> is not the only Example of a brutiſh valor attaining to a muſhrom grandeur: Nor was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44746:4"/>the puny Thief <hi>Du Val,</hi> the firſt Robber who lay in ſtate, by pompous folly to be made more inglorious.</p>
            <p>The Aerian ſtalking Nag (on whom the ſubtil Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Phanaticiſm ſet their aim to ſhoot at Game Royal) had his Image order'd to be made by the grand Boglers at Ceremonies, and Decryers of Superſtition; which intended for an Honor, made him to ſuffer <hi>in effigie</hi> for a Traitor; while a freak-inſpir'd Sectary cut off an head equally ſtupid, with that which he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to the vain Idol of a Fooliſh Reformation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Protector</hi> of Flies, carried in ſtate like to a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Deity, might ſeem worſhipped by an Heatheniſh Idolatry; while our Gentiles Schiſms fly-blows ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gain'd wings by the warmth of his bounty, with buzzing acclamations attended on their <hi>Belzebub.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ziſca</hi> would have a Drum made of his skin; and our Glorious <hi>Edward</hi> would have his victorious Corps carried for a terror to his Enemies: but nothing can be more vain than to take a pleaſure in the hovering of thoſe dire vapors above ground, who might ſeem to have cleft it for contagion.</p>
            <p>Vainly the dead are embalm'd with ſpices, whoſe lives can contribute no odors in good works to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume their memories.</p>
            <p>The Survivors worſhip of the dead was the wild Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition of Heathen. A commemoration of Saints
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44746:5"/>and Benefactors deceaſ'd, has bin neither the irteligious nor impolitick cuſtom of ſober Chriſtians. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor given to good men is a tribute render'd to God, who will be honor'd in his Saints; the praiſes of the bad are ſo many acknowledgments to Satan, who is thus worſhipped in his Images.</p>
            <p>The myſterious Riddle of Loyal Grandeur, whom ſome will have a Parent to his Mother, and his Fathers Father, a Prince the Father of his Country, the ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating <hi>Monk, G.</hi> D. of <hi>Albemarl,</hi> may worthily chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge that ſurviving honor, by which he ſeems trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant over Fate: if not a principal, an adjuvant, or ſuch a Cauſe without which our felicity could not be effected; if to vaſt Piles of living Honors were ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added mountains of wealth, and after death he is plac'd among Kings, who ſeem'd the Reſtorer of Kingdoms, no wiſe or good man can repine, but rather congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the felicity of that Age, in which a Servant eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Faithful, found a Maſter truly Royal. Honor was not made diſhonorable in our Generals ſuperadditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Titles: the atchievements of his Anceſtors, if not ſuperior to moſt, inferior to few Coats of Arms born by our Engliſh Nobility; what might give a ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, and Fools will be always the moſt apt to bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, the only blot in the Eſcutcheon. Honor muſt be fair written, ev'n the Fountain of it, a Prince, cannot waſh away the blemiſhes of his own making.</p>
            <p>The Generous Heroe who diſdain'd to bring in a King, fetter'd like a Royal Slave, or ſuch a Beaſt as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44746:5"/>muſt not be allowd the uſe of Reaſon whoſe Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is in Relation to the making of him a Sacrifice, by not attending to that rigid zeal, which (inſeparable from envy of any greatneſs which might exceed her own) would have Kings bound in chains, and their Nobles in fetters of iron; the intolerable Gives of a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> League, by making Princes Parties, can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne, not only level with a Peaſant, but equal to a Brute: if giddy Fame was only conſtant to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, none could think Honor or Riches miſplac'd with our General, except ſuch who can believe cruelties ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding that of the <hi>Goths, Huns</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> confer'd on the Preſerver of his Country, a recompenſe worthy of a <hi>Bellizarius.</hi> The devouring of a Serpent would be thus thought to produce a Dragon. Our <hi>George</hi> might not have ſeem'd to conquer a Monſter, but to have introduc'd one, in Ingratitude equalling that moſt monſtrous piece of Barbariſm, the miſchief brooding Part, which venting nothing but noiſe and ſtench, in the Opinion of Buffoons could be eſteem'd more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable than the Head.</p>
            <p>He who reſtored the Fountain of Honor untainted, none can juſtly envy a liberal benefit of the Streams; or who would deny ſome larger cluſters of Grapes to him, by whoſe beneficence they ſeem to have the uninterru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted enjoyments of their Vines?</p>
            <p>Neceſſity renders the proudeſt Titles contemptible; when an Emperor became a Souldier to our Eighth <hi>Henry,</hi> it might ſeem a timely magnificence which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44746:6"/>made a Princes bounties ſhine in a Tent, made with cloath of gold: The Prince who undervalues himſelf or Benefactors by becoming cheap, his Kingdoms and Armies rarely want Purchaſers.</p>
            <p>The Drums muſt beat, Trumpets ſound, and Images of Gold be rear'd to make the People fall down and worſhip: Yet where worldly pelf are the only Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, wiſe men can rather ſuffer the fiery furnace of affliction, than pay a Devotion to ſuch fooliſh Idols.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Speeds</hi> Chronicle hath a Remarque, That he who thought himſelf a match for Princes, the Low Country Prince, or truer King of Gypſies, the Arch-canter and chief Idol of the Aerians, who patroniz'd holy Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites as ſure friends to Religion, as he was to the moſt boſom friend, whoſe neck they could well contented break, to make way for the eſpouſing of a Whimzy, the great E. of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> the ſo much celebrated Favourite living, unmask'd by death, could want a commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Death only makes true Confeſſions. A little loſs of air, (or as much breath as can furniſh out a bubble vaniſh'd) leaves the moſt wind-impoſtum'd bladder ſhrivel'd. What equals all men, lends an impartial view, and unlearns the mannerly diſtinctions betwixt a Prince and Peaſant. <hi>Homer;</hi> though the Father of fictions, may gain a ſober belief, while he will have Hare to inſult over dead Lyons: but Envy cannot blaſt juſt actions, which (as a minor Poet) <hi>in the dust can ſmell ſweet and bloſſom.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:44746:6"/>
            <p>Who undervalued life in his Countreys Cauſes, Lillies and Roſes may be ſaid to ſpring from the Tomb of a no leſs renowned Hero, who dar'd to do as much in the Sea, as <hi>Curtius</hi> in the Land, for his Country.</p>
            <p>Some will have the firſt Degree of Reviv'd Loyalty commenc'd at the <hi>Three Tuns;</hi> and can dare publickly to aver, That there is a Knight who being inſpir'd by the ſame ſpirit of Loyal Sack, will ſwear himſelf the Author of our ſo Happy Reſtoration, and that Loyalty or Ruine were the only choice left to the <hi>General.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Serpent which gave us the Sting, muſt afford us the Cure: Some will not be perſuaded that the <hi>Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto</hi> which made him a Cypher in Commiſſion, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted no vote to their own Ruine, by putting a Period to his, gave a date to their own ſupereminent Power; and thus the cunning were catcht in their own ſnare: Yet he who infatuates the Council of the worldly wiſe, hath the leſt returns of Honor or Praiſe, where moſt forgetting God can ſuppoſe a Sacrifice due to every fooliſh Net.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>F.</hi> (anagram'd by <hi>Hei! fax fato Mars</hi>) if not the greateſt, no ſlender perſuaſion will allow, none of the meaneſt Inſtruments by riſing on the back of <hi>Lambert,</hi> and thus to have nobly expiated that brutiſh Folly, (not to give it a worſe name) which ſuffer'd us to be depriv'd of the beſt of Princes.</p>
            <p>I have bin no infrequent (though for the moſt part
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44746:7"/>an incredulous) Auditor of a Baronet who would have the <hi>General</hi> at his inlargement from the Tower, crave a benediction from Biſhop <hi>Wren,</hi> and aſſurd' him, when opportunity was propitious, he ſhould not be averſe to the Royal Service: Neither was this a ſingle Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which he had receiv'd from his Loyal Father, but another muſt be attendant on it equally irrefra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable, a promiſe to his Loyal Comrades, <hi>viz.</hi> never to bear Arms in <hi>England</hi> againſt his Prince: This not a few will have moſt exactly to be perform'd; and hence by no action of his Loyalty to be impeach'd: What he acted in the firſt Dutch Ingagement, and what was performed in the <hi>Caledonian</hi> War, muſt by a milder gloſs be interpreted a Zeal for his Country, and no diſaffection to his King; but the more rigid Cenſors will not allow him who wounds in hands and feet no Enemy, though not equally mortal with him who tranſpierces the heart.</p>
            <p>A ſuperintendent Lord would be a Privado to thoſe proceedings, which might call the wiſeſt brains into queſtion to imagin: But coming from ſo ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently knowing a Statiſt, and told in Parliament, he may ſeem wanting to all Reaſon, could be deficient in the belief of our <hi>Generals</hi> intention for a Reſtauration. I have heard a Kinſman and Retainer to his Lordſhip aver the ſight of the Letter.</p>
            <p>Whether <hi>O. C. L. &amp;c.</hi> have not complemented with vain hopes ſuch as they never intended ſhould reap any benefit above that of a deluded Imagination,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44746:7"/>is the Diſcourſe of no unwary, if none of the wiſeſt Heads.</p>
            <p>The Supplement of a Chronicle (which ſome can think may want a ſtout <hi>Peter Heylin,</hi> who blind, might beſt gueſs at dark intrigues) muſt be incontrollable to evince the truth of thoſe intents. A Chronicles name paſſes with ſome graver Noddles, for an Authority e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualling that which the Vulgar Creed hath for a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lad, which their Wiſdoms conceive as authentick as the Divineſt Writ.</p>
            <p>There are vaſt diſproportions (if not a Gulf equalling that which ſeparated the Rich man from an <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom) betwixt ſuch who write to give God the Honor, and thoſe who arrogate Divine Honor to their fooliſh Imaginations. The Heroe in the Romance muſt paſs ſtrange dangers, encounter Monſters, Magicians, and Giants in difficulties, be at a precipice for ruine, before Miracles are call'd in for his Deliverance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> who writ Commentaries on his own Actions, though none of the worſt, might not be the trueſt of Hiſtorians. Opinion puts falſe Spectacles on our eyes: both ſelf-intereſt and ſelf-conceit rarely not diſeaſe our ſights; and make us reſemble Jetericks, who can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend no colour beſide their own.</p>
            <p>Some will have it to be number'd among thoſe rarely numerable Infelicities of Loyalty, to be huff'd by every Braggart, not only out of the Tributes which ſhould be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44746:8"/>inſeparable from Virtue; but muſt be ever incapable of Worldly Compaſſion, unleſs loſt to that Reaſon which ſhould difference from Brutes. The fooliſh things of this world thus in no Chriſtian ſenſe may ſeem to confound the wiſe; but they who with a grain of Salt, have only a mite of Charity, may pitty, not envy, gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs advanc'd to ſlippery precipices.</p>
            <p>Though a Sober Doctor, in the languiſhing ſtate of the Body Politick, might not be uſeleſs; ſome will not allow the metamorphoſ'd Apothecary by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Honor, loſt to one, while he provided ſawce with ſippets of his own, to make an harſh parcel of Chronicle be more eaſily digeſted. A merry tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Chirurgian, who pretends an equal intimacy in tranſactions about State Ulcers, (if truth is in wine) might be believ'd, who would have a Broomſtick with a rag at end of it, to have bin of ſufficient efficacy for the Miracle of a Revolution.</p>
            <p>The Phanatick <hi>O.</hi> (whoſe name might imply his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine fit for lighter grounds) having bin baffled about a miſquoted piece of the Apocalyps, was ſarcaſtically ask'd by a Lord, at the <hi>Generals</hi> Table, whether he was converted out of the <hi>Revelations?</hi> to which he boldly reply'd to the Grandee, equally through all times gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, That it was not the <hi>Revelation,</hi> but the happy <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution</hi> to which they all ow'd their Converſions.</p>
            <p>That Nature ſhould produce nothing more reſerved than our Engliſh Heroe, will ſeem not the leaſt of our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44746:8"/>Nations Wonders, when ſome can impute that crime to him which makes all things more perlucid than glaſs; and others will have ſuch not infrequent perturbations impetuouſly moving in giddy paſſions, as not to permit the greateſt ſecrets inconſpicuous.</p>
            <p>The marrying of a Neece to a Regicides ſon, might call Loyalty in queſtion, did we not live in ſuch an Age of Wonders, where nothing can ſeem ſtrange: ſome can caſt away, what others can think a fooliſh pitty, on a Lady born of Loyal Parents, who apprehend not the Myſteries of fleſh and bloud, or rather thoſe tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ones of the late times.</p>
            <p>It is no leaſt piece of Charity (if ſome may be credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) to believe he never intended that Reſtauration, of which he was made an happy Inſtrument. His own priſtine Loyalty, and that of his untainted Brothers (by conſanguinity, not alliance) might prediſpoſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imbibing of ſo long eſtranged Allegiance: but many ſwim with the ſtream, who dare not oppoſe an adverſe Torrent.</p>
            <p>Report will have the E. of <hi>L.</hi> drolling to have told the <hi>D.</hi> that he could never have heartily curſed him in his life except once, and that was when he beat down the City Gates; to whom he merrily reply'd, That while he was doing the work of his Maſters, they turn'd him out of Commiſſion, but he conciev'd himſelf to have bin even with them. <hi>Ridentem dicere verum, quid vetat?</hi> can be the queſtion of more than a ſingle <hi>Horace.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:44746:9"/>
            <p>A Perſon of great and ſober Honour, (who rarely could find a Peer, in that unhappy juncture, either in Eſtate or loyally ingag'd Relations) aſſur'd with voice and geſture expreſſing horror and indignation, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of good could be expected from this Man, neither by his Agents in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by homebred or exotick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, the leaſt glimpſe of hopes could ariſe: but a ſudden Revolution taught a Palinode; he had long expected nothing leſs from ſo worthy a Perſon. The Shepheard who would be reputed weather-wiſe, by telling one it would be fair, and another foul, in all weathers kept his reputation. Our late times can ſhow no few ſucceſsful imitators of this trifling Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, who to this fooliſh craft ow the opinion of their grand wiſdoms.</p>
            <p>In the ſo much celebrated March from the North, nigh <hi>Dunſtable,</hi> having an opportunity of treating ſome of his Commanders, one of the, a perſon neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociable, nor of that rigidly moroſe humor, which is inſeparable from Faction, inform'd me he could not ſufficiently admire at the univerſal kindneſs which they encounter'd in the March from <hi>Scotland.</hi> If a King was in the Deſign, nothing could be more vain than the peoples imaginations: ſince neither the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral nor his Followers could think of it without hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; and that I might relinquiſh vain and fruitleſs hopes, thought himſelf oblig'd in civility and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to inform of the Oath taken in <hi>Scotland,</hi> nothing differing from that which ſince put out by Phanaticks, I have peruſ'd in print, not without a new impreſſion of horror.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:44746:9"/>
            <p>Chriſtianity will induce us to believe, that neither the <hi>General</hi> nor his Army were guilty of that Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Policy, which calls God in for a witneſs to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly. Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs inſtills new thoughts: men have the changes of mind with the viciſſitudes of Fortune. Factions like other Traders inrich'd by unexpected returns, diſdain all partnerſhip, divide and drive different Intereſts. How eaſily do thoſe ſpeculations which ſeemed as high as heaven, ſtoop to the Lure of every phancy'd profit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> though he ſnatch'd at a Crown in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, could not expect to gain one by the Tragedies acted over three Nations. The E. of <hi>Eſſex</hi> who would ſeem clear from the ſuſpition of Treaſon againſt Q. <hi>E.</hi> would not deny that ſucceſs might have made a Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
            <p>They who fear'd not man might ſuppoſe it in vain to conteſt with the Deity. The <hi>General</hi> and his Army heard in their Expedition the Voice of the People, like that of God, they found the ſinews of war were wanting; and though the Chains, Gates and Poſts of the City were caſt down, the ſpirits of the Citizens were inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected: who had ingag'd to reſtore a Parliament to freedom and honor, it had bin perjury not to have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd it, though ſome will have the act a high vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Faith, deſerted firſt to relinquiſh the patch'd piece of folly with the Appellative.</p>
            <p>The Army introduc'd no King; but having ſettled a more rationally ſuppoſ'd Parliament in freedom, acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſced
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44746:10"/>in the determinations of their Superiors: and thus the true Souldiers of King and Parliament finiſh'd without their cruel aid, the War ſo long protracted by perjury, rapine and bloud.</p>
            <p>It may ſeem a cruel piece of Charity to deprive of Chriſtianity, for the better intitling to Grace and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency. Who came at the laſt hour in the Goſpel, was allotted a reward equalling that of the firſt comers. Such converts as are the joy of Angels, ſhould not be the Envy of men.</p>
            <p>Some will have the Low-Country a Nurſery for Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, but the moſt unſucceſsful Academy for Religion and Loyalty: who expoſ'd their ſouls and bodies Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenaries to in the cauſe of a Rebellious Commonwealth were vainly expected good Subjects to a Prince.</p>
            <p>Generous perſons, are apt to entertain their Title in their belieſs, can ſuppoſe our <hi>General</hi> no ignoble Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or of Fortune, who fighting long under her colours, at length attain'd the giddy Idol for his conſtant Miſtreſs. He deſerted no Maſters, till they deſerted him; a Low-Country Religion both oblig'd him to a Party, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblig'd; when he wanted an exchange for Loyalty, he exchang'd it; and when giddy Patriots of the then eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed Cauſe, were return'd fairly to take away his Commiſſion, he as honorably relinquiſh'd the deſerters of themſelves and him.</p>
            <p>It is a blaſphemy to affirm him a Deity, though we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44746:10"/>may juſtly allow him an <hi>Hannibal,</hi> a <hi>Fabius,</hi> an <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,</hi> a worth equalling, if not ſuperexcelling all the Antient <hi>Heroes:</hi> ſome fooliſh Sycophants will intitle to more wiſdom, than God ever intruſted to mere hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature; yet while they ſtrive to deifie, make him the Fool that ſaid in his heart, <hi>There is no God.</hi> He who can take Oaths, with an intention to violate them, it muſt be a ſtrange exceſs of Charity which can allow him a God in his Creed.</p>
            <p>General <hi>Leſhly</hi> told <hi>Potter</hi> a Trumpeter, ſent to him by the Royal Martyr, That he would ſerve his Majeſty as faithfully as he had done the Parliament: The Scot gain'd an eaſie belief, and in charity we may believe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended what he promiſed; he ſerved them for Money, and for gain (which was his Religion) would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ'd to ſale his Maſters. But while a neceſſitated Prince could not go the price, a King not to be equal'd by Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, is paſſed in exchange for Two hundred thouſand pound.</p>
            <p>Nothing is more pleaſant then the junior ſtory of this Bony <hi>Jocky,</hi> who ran away with blith <hi>Jenny,</hi> ſtealing ſixteen ſhillings <hi>ſterling</hi> from an old Miſtreſs at <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> to defray charges; yet by temptation of ſo vaſt a ſum, though much mowing and many Bearns, ſhe reap'd not Matrimony, till her fingers being as light as her heels, a plunder'd Portion made up the March which was a muckle day of joy, as the gude Counteſs told the Right Honourable Lady of <hi>Oxford,</hi> when her Husband from a common Soldier had arriv'd to be a Scotch Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44746:11"/>and by heading a Rebellion, became an Earl, to give a reputation to his future Villanies. Snakes though warm'd in the moſt Royal boſoms, will requite their entertainment with a ſting. Though Factions may ſeem to loſe their heads, which are taken off by Honor; yet they are rarely wanting to freſh opportunities for miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</p>
            <p>Our generous Champion, when he had eſpouſ'd Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and acquir'd deſerved Honor, by the evil principle of no mercenary ſpirit, made Conſcience a Proſtitute to the luſts of Faction.</p>
            <p>Who would wound our <hi>Heroe</hi> in the weakeſt part, find him there moſt impregnable. Honor, Conſcience and Gratitude appear in his vindication; and that cruel neceſſity which can make batteries on the ſtrongeſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions: none will phancy it brutiſh ſottiſhneſs, or that the moſt daring of men would be affrighted out of Reaſon, by an inconſiderate Huffer, the great tie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity which injoyns ſatisfaction, and the preſerving of a generous Family, famous through a long ſeries of Anceſtors, might be no leſſer inducements to Marriage. If in ſome things he reſembled an <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, in others he exceeded the more victorious <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> an Husband for all mens wives; excellent above his fam'd Anceſtor a Fourth <hi>Edward,</hi> or a <hi>Philip,</hi> who ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the Good, wanted his Virtue. Our <hi>Heroe</hi> was not captivated by that which inſlaves the proudeſt Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; and made him whoſe labours fill'd all the world, ridiculouſly to truckle to a diſtaff: in this a more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44746:11"/>than <hi>Hercules,</hi> who by an invincible fortitude, endur'd a Confinement which might intitle to a quotidian in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countring of Monſters, and not leſs frequent triumphs o'er wild Beaſts in Paſſions.</p>
            <p>In requital, if he found a Wiſe, not rich, ſhe made her ſelf ſo: ſome can phancy the riches accruing to her Husband, and Heir, by this frugal Womans means, made the proudeſt Dowry in three Nations ſcarſe her parallel for a Match. It was a rare felicity in Ages, when the Parents virtue was the childs dowry; who neither gain by inheritance nor acquiſition, are only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted contemptibly poor: where Money anſwers all things, Riches; where Worth, Virtue may ſeem the beſt portion and moſt acquirable of perfections.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Lycurgus</hi> Dogs ſeem to make an infallible demonſtration, they are too incharitable in their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, who can believe that no temptation either of gain or profit, could intervene, in which, with the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Cat in the Fable, the humor of mouſing not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd.</p>
            <p>It is reported of <hi>Theophilus,</hi> that he burnt a rich ſhip of his wives, diſdaining that the covetous folly of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould exchange the Title of an Emperour to that of a Merchant. Some can hope a more cruel Traffick found no acceptation from our Induperator: others can fear an Harpies Talons laden, were never an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Oblation.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:44746:12"/>
            <p>He who pluckt the Thorns out of the Crown, it is Charity to believe he would plant no new pricks, or Canaanites reſembling them, in his ſide, whom he had return'd to a Land of Promiſe.</p>
            <p>Who mov'd in ſo high a ſphere of Glory as our <hi>Heroe,</hi> could not but attract Clouds of Envy, which by their blacker interpoſure might vail that luſtre which they could not obſcure. Envious Folly, the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to miſtakes, rarely makes not more bright, what ſhe intends moſt to darken. A ſober ſcruteniſt may find our <hi>General</hi> the leſt conſcious of what the Rabbles Idol, Report, the Common Lyer, broaches from frothing hogſheads, either for advantage or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of Glory. The giddy Strumpet Fame, which is every Ideots Proſtitute, makes no ſtop betwixt the Extreams of Honor or Infamy: ſhe cheriſhes that which we intends to blaſt by the cold wind of an envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpleaſure; and, while active as fire, ſhe would gratifie Grandeur, conſumes what ſhe intends only to inliven by a warmer commendation.</p>
            <p>The ſelling of a Prince was a fatal Prognoſtick: may the ſale of Loyalty be more propitious. The God of this world did ſo dazle fooliſh eyes, that nothing was to be ſeen in the moſt Execrable Trator, beſide unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd Excellence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Treaſon was only a ſubtil reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedneſs, or a pious fraud for Royal advantage. The Mammon of unrightouſneſs was not imploy'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide Heav'nly places, but to promote Earthly intereſts. Some can think the greateſt Judas here, might have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44746:12"/>found no cauſe of deſperation, where ſo many Pieces might have intitled to Honor and Office. Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> may ſerve out of many Centuries of obſervations, who (a conſtant Servant to his Royal Maſter through all Changes) prov'd a Setter of <hi>Olivers,</hi> pearch'd high by Mammon, in this laſt and more happy Revolution de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faming him for diſloyalty; to have bin ſo grand a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſo on Record, as might evidence to have receiv'd no leſſer Stipends for annual courſes of Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Though he who makes haſt to be rich, cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; yet who would gueſs the greatneſs of guilt by the vaſtneſs of a contracted Treaſure, may be miſtaken in their Arithmetick. The <hi>Generals</hi> Offices of Profit, and Places of Honor, none can juſtly deny him; nor a wiſe man the frugal improvement: his Retinuo was rather beneficial than chargeable, who put neither to the Expences of Wages or Diet.</p>
            <p>The Courtiers and his own Servants, who revenge by their tongues the loſs which they have ſuſtained by their teeth, rarely ſpeak well of him, whom they will have the Author of Board-Wages at Court, and to have ſav'd half in his own daily allowance: The Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers ware, as ſacred, muſt be untoucht, if it met no maim at his Table, was injoyn'd, new roaſted, to reviſit it next day incompany. All Exceſſes are equally dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: if he obſerv'd the truly golden mean to inrich a Family, it could not be diſhonorable. The ſtory of <hi>Actaeon</hi> may ſeem no Fable, where the bloud of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies hath bin ſwallowed for their Healths, and the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44746:13"/>mercileſs teeth of a fawning Retinue have devour'd their Maſters. But among giddy Reports none can be more incredible, than the menacing of an only child with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inheriting for expending Five ſhillings at ſupper, in which ſum a Capon, a bottle of wine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beer, ale, roots, muſt be included: though perhaps wine might lend the only occaſion to the Paſſion, which he who allows to children, adds fire to fire; and by a fond indulgence contributes to the ruine of a Name, when debauch'd Nature, to quench the preternatural heat, renders them ſuch ſpunges, as orecharg'd by liquor, ſerve only to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punge their own and Anceſtors Glory. The Philoſopher would have crack'd his ſpleen to have ſeen vaſt piles of muck provided, &amp; the ground left unmanur'd, where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be wanting that well imploy'd might have render'd it ſertil. I knew a Pedant of ſo ſtrangely ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous a conſcience, that he could number it amongſt his ſins to make a Boy more learned than his Father, which he could ſuppoſe might unlearn him that duty which hath the promiſe of long life. It muſt be a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger portion of knowledg which can edifie for perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the traders in ſmall parcels gain only ſome windy inflations which can puff up; ſome will not allow it above a windy diſtemper, which ſo long diſcompoſ'd our body Politick, and made that duty forgot, which is a juſt tribute to the Parent of a Country.</p>
            <p>Not a few think of learning what <hi>Matchiavel</hi> ſays of Religion, That it is an impediment to great Actions. Blindneſs begets boldneſs, and folly muſt be intitled to fat and fortunate, or elſe the plump Schiſmatick could
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44746:13"/>not gain ſo great an Harveſt of fooliſh Ears, which every blaſt of falſe doctrine can teach to bow in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance to the moſt pernitious Ignorance.</p>
            <p>Folly may be pearch'd high, like the Fablers Crow, yet not ſecure from a Foxes Craſt: Our ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Reynards by provoking fools to cant, make the meat in their mouths a purchaſe; or fail not thus to gain themſelves food.</p>
            <p>Though the General had a mighty ſpirit (as I heard one phraſe it) the Woman was not ſo narrow ſoul'd as her Husband, if of any religion ſhe was a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian, in the time of the Plague ſent Five pound to a Non-conformiſt Sermon-maker; beſtow'd 12 d. a piece on fifty poor Widows; cauſ'd her Son to ſend two broad pieces for Plaiſters, to the goutie Verſifier of the Gang, whoſe feet were more deſervingly nimble for her: Lords honour in the Northern Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: they will not allow him a dragm of charity who caſt no mite into the treaſury of the Saints, but we can hope, though a Souldier, he coded not the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crits trumpets, and the Alms he gave in ſecret will be rewarded openly. However, while there are Churches, Colledges, Hoſpitals, or any publick Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of Charity he will be acknowledged a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, who ſeem'd to reſcue them from the jaws of that ſacrilegions Wolf, who would have glibly ſwallowed all things facred under the pretence of zeal and reformation.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:44746:14"/>
            <p>He could not be ignorant of the ſix thouſand pounds his Wife had intentionally devoted to an Alms-Houſe, which he made his own act by an Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it may be imputed to an improv'd Religion and Loyalty, if he grown wiſer by time was a leſs zealous Patron of thoſe pernitious Houſe-creepers, who lead ſilly Females captive, to whom a Paradiſe would be diſpleaſing without the taſte of prohibited fruit. If he took no care of what ſome can call the Houſhold of Faith, none can deny, worſe than an Infidel, by taking no care of his own Family; what ſome can call ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didneſs, if equally conſidered, may be found a noble frugality which would not leave ſo vaſt a Pudding contemptible for want of Suet.</p>
            <p>Some will affix to a greater Statiſt then our General, the Maxim on which the <hi>Indians</hi> ground the neglect of God, and the worſhipping of the Devil: but evil Council is ever worſt to the Councellory; the cunning are rarely not catched in their own ſnare; and he who digs a pit for Loyaly may fall ſo deeply in, as the moſt loyal may find no Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>There are who will not allow the greateſt preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Loyalty to have had an equally obliging nature with that of the Pikes, who devour their own kind laſt: where the Proverb will have a Dog lov'd for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſake, he who could but ſnarl and bark in the Cauſe, &amp; knew never how to fawn on his enemies; to be be loſt to all reſpect, might call the Grand Monopolizers of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44746:14"/>Loyalties truth into queſtion. Many could have been content to have dy'd, that others might enjoy that ſight to whoſe enjoyment they ow'd a cruel death. It can be no Paradox to aver, that ſincere Loyalty can never want either a Friend or Reward; and yet what is moſt ſtrange, that contradictory aſſertion may ſeem equally true, that to no fucated Loyaliſts the moſt wiſh't for of Reſtaurations, by the extirpation of more loyal Families, hath prov'd a more fatal enemy then the War. In a baptiſmal vow we renounc'd the World, the Fleſh and the Devil: Ingaged in the Royal Cauſe, we might ſeem to fight againſt thoſe three grand An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſts; if the younger Brothers in Loyaltie, who had waſted their Patrimonies on the Harlots of Schiſm, and could be content, like the Swine, to be fed with the husks of every falſe doctrine; if the return'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digals are receiv'd into favour, why ſhould the elder Brothers repine, having the aſſurance of a promiſe; no wiſe man would trifle away time to gather Cockles on the Shore, when he may ſet ſails unto another Country, where are no fickle joys, hopes, or fears, but an <hi>Enge Beate</hi> is made the prologue to eternal Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity.</p>
            <p>Nothing is more comical then to ſee our Apes of Loyal Grandeur; how ſtately are the deportments of fooliſh Mimicks, till the ſcrambling for Nuts expoſes ridiculous? <hi>Lucretius</hi> would have it no leſſer pleaſure ſecure on the Shore, to contemplate afar off men toſſ'd on the Sea: Who will be laden with this worlds Merchandiſe are the ſubjects of Winds and Waves,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44746:15"/>which ſeem to ſing and ſport in their ruines; they are the objects of a Fools envy, but the Wiſemans pity, who expoſe frail Barks to encounter all ſtorms.</p>
            <p>Some can fancy our <hi>Heroe,</hi> tho Wheel to which we owe all the viciſſitudes of giddie Greatneſs, ſay alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately he was an enemy to the two ſupereminently Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Statiſts; and will have a third with the loſs of Land (which he ever valued, like to it ſelf, dirt) pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe with a place the deluſion of a pleaſing dream.</p>
            <p>The Gordian Knot, which none could untie, an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> could out, but it is reported of an angry Lord, <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>P.</hi> that being in office, he made it his buſineſs to break wiſer heads then his own. Though ſome praiſe our Generals conduct to the making of Hyperboles modeſt, others will have his head-piece the worſt part of his Armor. Who pretend to be moſt knowing in thoſe affairs, to think that <hi>Oliver</hi> either could fear there, or be ignorant how to remove him from his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in <hi>Scotland,</hi> is accounted the moſt ridiculous part in his Story: to <hi>C.</hi> he muſt have been like one of the Centurions ſervants; a mutinous Sea-man muſt have found it true by the experiment of a loſt Noſe, which to patch up coſt him and <hi>Oliver</hi> ten Pieces.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Heroe</hi> never wanted reſolution, which is the beſt ſword in War. Had his head been as good as his heart, the Nick-named Protector told C. <hi>Okey, England</hi> would have been too little to have contain'd a <hi>Nol</hi> and a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44746:15"/>
               <hi>Jack;</hi> but heads and hearts holding ſo unequal a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, the ſecure Tyrant might domineer o're three diſtracted Nations. Some, like Chymiſts, by the advantage of other mens heads may do miracles, who are uſeleſs with their own, not above tunnels for ſmoak, yet by fumes inſpir'd, pretend to all things.</p>
            <p>Whom not a few have call'd a delaying <hi>Fabius,</hi> many can think he would have fought with a daring <hi>Hannibal</hi> upon any diſadvantage; when neither the odds of number, nor a contradictorie Commiſſion could hinder from the diſadvantageous ingagement with the <hi>Dutch. Militemus</hi> was an Emperours <hi>Motto,</hi> let us fight Boys, our more undaunted Generals; war was his element, and out of it he might ſeem like a Fiſh out of water.</p>
            <p>The opinion of the Stoicks can animate Turks to brave death in War, and in place intrepid to converſe with the moſt fatal Contagion. Our <hi>Heroe</hi> by ſtranger revolutions might be eaſily induc'd to embrace the doctrine of an inevitable wheel, who could dreadleſs look down on dangers, fear neither of thoſe Bug-b ears to Mankind, A Plague, or War, ſo much a Proſelite to the Predeſtination principle, as to think it moſt ridiculous to fly that fate which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable.</p>
            <p>A Knight related to our <hi>G.</hi> dehorted him from the Belgick War, as having done already enough for the immortality of a Name. To whom he repli'd, he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44746:16"/>was ſent into the world upon an Errand which muſt be performed, and whether it might end at the bottom of the Sea, as it was incertain, ſo it ſhould not find him concern'd. Some will have our <hi>Heroe</hi> like the Poets <hi>Ajax,</hi> who diſdain'd to be vincible by any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept himſelf, and will have it ſo near the finiſhing his errand in the Sea, as Guns were placed to ſink ſo great a weight of Glory.</p>
            <p>Who conquered the World could not ſubdue his Paſſions: Thoſe mutinying Rebels can domineer o're the reputed Invincible; ſome will have Thunder and Lightning in our incenſed <hi>Heroe</hi>'s breath, and that he was leaſt what he perſwaded others to be (in his journey from the North) of a ſedate temper; rather than peace ſhould be with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> he ſaid he would never wear a Sword. A more ſober Stateſman is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to have repli'd, he had rather lay aſide his Gown, then that ſo unneceſſary a War ſhould be commenc'd; inform'd him our want of Allies abroad, and Moneys, Wars Sinews, which can give ſtrength to the moſt enfeebled Arms, make firm Friends at home, and aſſure forreign Alliances; the wiſe Man knew, though God and a good Cauſe makes a great ſound, it is the tinkling noiſe of coyn doth the Souldiers bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; and however juſtice is pretended in all Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it is to Gold, the worlds great Idol, men are content not only to make the ſacrifice of Fools them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but even their neareſt Relations.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:44746:16"/>
            <p>War is not only ſweet to them who never try'd it, but to ſuch who have reaped a benefit by it: a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier can love his Harveſt. Some cannot arrive to his wiſdom, who went out of the world with a <hi>Thou fool,</hi> with full barns he could have bin contented his ſoul ſhould have took her eaſe.</p>
            <p>We have had the War, by which the Kingdom is ſo many Millions in debt; our <hi>Heroe</hi> in probability might have loſt his Sword, and if he had bin a Dutchman, might have forfeited his Head, which renounc'd not only Reaſon, but ev'n Loyalty, by raſhly exceeding of his Commiſſion: Yet the extremity of Law might thus have prov'd the ſupreme injury. If it was Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in our <hi>General</hi> (as in the caſe of a E of <hi>Eſſex,</hi>) it was a venial delinquency; if a Traitor, he was the beſt meaning; whoſe ſuperabundant or zeal or valour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded of an Ingagement, by the miſtaken propoſition of the accruing honour and ſafety to his Prince and Country, in whoſe Cauſe his Noble, though here not beſt inform'd Spirit, could have bin content to have finiſh'd an Errand in Waves, the beſt Emblems of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant Greatneſs and giddy Fortunes Favours. The method by which he ſeem'd to reſtore, he might have ſecur'd his Country: here a <hi>Fabius,</hi> he might have effected by delays, what he could not by fighting; and have ſeem'd a double Reſtorer of this Nation, whoſe raſhneſs might have intitled the Demoliſher.</p>
            <p>It cannot be the leſt wiſdom not to think to do always the ſame things. Empirical, or valor, or medicine, not rarely ſucceſleſs.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:44746:17"/>
            <p>Storms ſucceed the cleareſt Sunſhine; which a wiſe man foreſeeing, like to the victorious <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, quits the Stage.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Cromwell</hi> had fell from his Coach, a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of his was overhear'd to complain, that he who had raiſ'd, would ruine them, if a timely care was not taken to prevent the expoſure of his wild freaks. Death was a timely friend, nigh to the end of his wits, was near to the end of his life; and thus finiſh'd what <hi>Mazarine</hi> call'd the moſt fortunate piece of Folly.</p>
            <p>Some will have him who could be content to reſign his Gown, rather than there ſhould have bin a War, to be forc'd to reſign becauſe it prov'd ſucceſleſs.</p>
            <p>Men rarely can be pleaſ'd with his company, whoſe looks may upbraid their miſcarriages. The incenſ'd Rabble, like to Heathen Idols, muſt have humane blood for a Sacrifice; though the ſooliſh overflowings of their Galls can be pacified by no more grateful oblation than that, by which they expreſs all ills, Ingratitude; ſeldom not gratified by his Ruine, who might moſt ſeek their Preſervation.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Strafford</hi> was allow'd to be no Preſident, yet ſome will ever propoſe him for an Example; and no Act of Oblivion will make us ſo loſt to our memories, that the moſt unfortunate Earl will be forgot, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably loyal, was impeach'd by ſuch Arch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, as by introducing the <hi>Scots,</hi> were guilty of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44746:17"/>higheſt Treaſon, the moſt implacable enemy of Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors fell their ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>When putrid members were to be cut off, the body politick was depriv'd of the ſounder part, which might have ſecur'd it from encroaching miſchiefs, while an unparallel'd Princes clemency, which gave fears to none, and left not the greateſt villanies deſtitute of hopes, adminiſter'd in the Grand Stateſmans ruine, if not a juſt, an unhappy cauſe of his own untimely period.</p>
            <p>The gratifying of the weakeſt heads, with the loſs of the wiſeſt, as a moſt bloody, ſo is rarely not a moſt ſucceſleſs Policy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Athenians</hi> might be thought to have a venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for an Owl only, who could eſtrange Worth by an Oſtraciſm.</p>
            <p>Some will have the greateſt of Engliſh Statiſts to have periſh'd by their own weapons. One wiſe head, like <hi>Galba</hi>'s wit, not ill plac'd, may exceed in value not only many Millions of Money, but Armies of Men.</p>
            <p>Good intelligence, and bold truth ſome ſay could unfix a no undeſerving relation of the Generals, whom nothing, except his diſpleaſure, unrivited from the greateſt office of Truſt; in which the Succeſſor may ſeem not the leaſt of State Riddles; but myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Grandeur is ſuch an Abyſs, as Fools will fondly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44746:18"/>gueſs at the depth of that which the Plumets of the moſt comprehenſive reaſons can never fathom.</p>
            <p>Some who are uncapable of the diviner myſteries, can put themſelves to the troubleſom admiration how the extemporary traſh of a canting and long winded Schiſmatick in a Chamber, can be preparatory to the more ſober devotion of the Chappel-Royal? or how the truly Loyal and religious Grandee's, our incomparable Converts, can keep Chaplains to aſſert with paper pellets that ſchiſm to which they muſt be the greateſt ſtrangers, if not eſtranged to their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance; and to defile their new honours have not ſuck't up their old vomits? The Actors on the worlds Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by ſhifting Cloaks and Beards act different parts, and interchangeably fill up the Play of life with cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitous ſcenes of miſery, or ridiculous interludes.</p>
            <p>Nothing is more pleaſant in our revolutions then to hear the grand enemies of the Prerogative, and the Lordly Branches, the moſt confident aſſertors of the Priviledges which the King and Lords may moſt juſtly challenge; and the ſame perſons formerly could moſt unjuſtly impugn: who deprived the Throne of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters will ever ſtand in need of one to cleave to, and ſecur'd by the Unicorn can be dreadleſs of the Lyon. The leaſt Friends of the loyal Clergie will ever want the benefit of it in a Pſalm of mercy. How appoſite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the Princes Prerogative pleaded in the favour of ſciſm by the Protoſticklers of it, which would allow him none in Religion? And yet thus they can hope a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44746:18"/>priviledge for ſuch as void both of tenderneſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to its Prince, could deny him a liberty they would have indulg'd to the meaneſt Subjects.</p>
            <p>There may be no improbable conjecture as well as other Grandees, a confident ignorance might eaſily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on our <hi>Heroe.</hi> The intruſting ſo valued a body with ſuch an illiterate quack, as ſome would have diſdain'd to have made the Farrier to a beloved or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Beaſt, lend no ſmall ſuſpicion; the Patronage of the Stroaker ſome will have a too pregnant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
            <p>Age, in it ſelf an invincible diſeaſe, might aſſure no eaſie conqueſt of a concomitant diſtemper, which might be intitled old: yet twenty years of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annuation, and twelve of deafneſs, were eſteemed inconſiderable in a nonagenarian woman, when a wonder-working hand could appear for the recovery, the Stroaker <hi>G.</hi> and ſent by the General to reſtore her ſo long eſtranged Hearing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon Magus, Apollonius, Pere grinus Philoſophus, Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Paphlago,</hi> who appear'd with lying wonders to give a diſrepute to Primitive Chriſtianity, could not be more confident then this gracious babe of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Reformation: while the Puritans accuſe the Papiſts for their holy Maid of <hi>Kent,</hi> they forget <hi>Elizabeth Barton</hi> their Wench in the Wall: As if ſtroaking could cicure the wildeſt Adverſaries, every party hath been provided by a thus trifling Impoſtor.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:44746:19"/>
            <p>Men in power ſhould not make themſelves conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous by ſuch a bruitiſh connivence as calls Gods and his Vicegerents Honours into queſtion.</p>
            <p>The bold folly of Stroakers may ſeem a mocking of Majeſty, and the intrenching on that Prerogative, which conferr'd by a St. <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, and a St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> on the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> to cure by touch, muſt be reputed ſacred, ſuch a Jewel as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be alienated from a Crown.</p>
            <p>Miracles need not be call'd into the Scene, where natural cauſes can be aſcrib'd: Stronger frictions can cure ſome intercutaneous Maladies, ſhould the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of a ſweating Palm be deni'd conducive by the effluviums of wonder-working Atoms.</p>
            <p>A Knight, a Relation to the Duke, and Son to the Grandeve Patient of the Stroaker, gratifying my curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity with the converſe of the Trifler, I heard him as confidently propoſe <hi>Moſes</hi> an example for his doing of Miracles, as if he had been to lead the Jewiſh Tribes of Phariſaical Presbyterians through a Red Sea into a Land of Promiſe: and the Invaſion of <hi>France</hi> being then noiſ'd, the Engliſh by a cunning Man might hope the recovery of what they had loſt by a wiſe Woman. If the Braggar't, or a vouching Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade were to be believ'd, the General was ſo indear'd by the recovery of his Kinſwomans eye, that he would not allow him a nights abſence to gratifie the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of Relations.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:44746:19"/>
            <p>Sinking men will take hold of Reeds. Stroaking, which could hear abominable ſuperſtition and Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal contrivance in the Papiſts, muſt give a reparation to the declining cauſe of Presbyterians: The wonder-working Lieutenant was the moſt affecting diſcourſe of that party, which had he been of a different phancy for his lying wonders they would have intitled him an Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Whom ſome would have a Candidate for a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Cap, others will have Probationer for a Fools, while he could countenance a ſtroaking Friar to enter conteſt with a Prince, and ſhow a Chappel leſs effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious for miracles then a Banquetting-houſe.</p>
            <p>It not a little perplex'd Sir <hi>K. D.</hi> and made not a few merry, that an eminent Churchman with an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Title, and the not diſingenious Son of a Grand <hi>Virtuoſo,</hi> expoſ'd an innocent to danger, and themſelves to be ridiculous. The ſolemn Pageantry which attended the ſimple Iriſh Prieſts ſtroaking to wiſer heads of their own profeſſion, ſeem'd a diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on rivalling theirs, who with Kettles afford their tinckling Charity to the Moon in an Ecclyps.</p>
            <p>Who ſince the Reſtauration gain'd to his Right Honourable Title, a blew Ribband, and in ſome opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions was intitled to a refin'd wit, and grand Polititian, the late times report the Patient and Admirer of a ſtroaking Lunatick, the unhappy Stroaker, whoſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44746:20"/>diſturbed brains for their recovery might want more drugs then an <hi>Anticyra</hi> could furniſh, which ſo long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded the moſt active endeavours of Medicine, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſevereſt diſcipline of <hi>Bedlam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who can wonder if natures rude draught, a Soldier poliſh'd by no Art, impoſ'd on by proud Ignorance and giddie Fame, might give a Stroakers folly a Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus, where the wiſeſt Heads might have their Judgments call'd in queſtion by their hands. Deſert is not only unattended on by a Mandamus, but rarely encounters an unbrib'd Commendation. Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty heads make the greateſt ſound, and full purſes the moſt ſignificant noyſe for Preferment. A Phanatick Trooper, who might be loſt to all knowledge, if he had not plunder'd it from Loyalty, whoſe Library was not above a <hi>Barrows Method,</hi> and an Almanack, two Doctors hands requir'd for the granting of a licence to practiſe Phyſick, he produc'd an obſolete Manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus from the grand Protector of Ignorance, <hi>Cromwel,</hi> which in the worſt of times had not the confidence to viſit <hi>Oxford,</hi> in the beſt durſt encounter the moſt learn'd Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon,</hi> who in vain could reſiſt it, ten Angels powerfully appearing to his Chancellour, were ſatisfactory motives to make by the golden rule of practiſe a true Licentiate.</p>
            <p>The Shcools can make it diſputable whether what was intended the greateſt encourager of Virtue, hath not been the leaſt acquainted with Merit. Learning and Loyalty put beyond all diſpute, brought to the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44746:20"/>teſt, would be rarely found above in the ſees and Mandamus of not a few booted Fiſhermen for degrees (as they call them) which are catch't by a golden hook. Looſers may have a prating licence: If a few complain, many have cauſe to praiſe this golden Age. He muſt be wiſe who is rich, or ſome whoſe mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpirits can give ſo glib a commendation to the moſt deplorable pieces of Folly, may be queſtion'd for that wiſdom which makes fools and themſelves equally fortunate.</p>
            <p>Worldly Grandeur, with the not misbecoming at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of Right Honourable and Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſometimes can have a too unhappy reſemblence to Pagan Idols, which having eyes and ears, neither hear nor ſee.</p>
            <p>Whoſe wiſdom lyes in another mans head (who can be blind and deaf for intereſt) may make a comment on that Text, which will have man being in honour compar'd to the beaſts which periſh wathout under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>Some will have our Engliſh <hi>Solomon</hi> in pain, to have liſten'd to a Woman for a Remedy. There are who gueſs by the touchſtone of Phyſick, whoſe ignorance might exceed a Phanaticks Sermon, not the only Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick who attended our <hi>Heroe. France, France,</hi> often repeated in the opinion of a <hi>Francis,</hi> could equal the titles of an Emperour: to excuſe his miſtakes, and make a parallel for all worthies, we may repeat the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44746:21"/>
               <hi>Souldier, Souldier:</hi> Some think they honour moſt in making no Souldier, but an uncommiſſion'd and peaceable Spectator to the moſt happy of Revolutions.</p>
            <p>When the ſtinking part offenſive to moſt noſtrils, had her Presbyterian appurtenances adjoyn'd, which long laid aſide for ſweetning, had not depoſited their rankneſs to clear Noſes; One of their prime votes was, that no man ſhould be capaple of Office, who would not ſubſcribe Rebellion lawful, for by a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary illation it is deducible, if a war againſt the King was juſt: I have heard ſome, not of ſo ill inform'd judgments, as to believe the levelling of a war againſt a Prince not Treaſon, yet ſo looſe principl'd in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they would aſſert all Oaths and Subſcriptions lawful, which might render capable of ſerving the Royal Intereſt; ſuch tools were as profitable to Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty as the Gnoſticks to Chriſtianity. He who dares not truſt God, in vain may be credited by man. To play the Devil for God ſake hath been a common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, but was never enter'd for an Article in a ſober Belief.</p>
            <p>Who could glory in being Confeſſors, and could think to ſuffer in the Cauſe of God, their King and Countrey, Martyrdom, Air and Dirt, Life and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, were contemptible trifles to them, who could propoſe white Robes in confeſſion and Purple in their ſufferings, which might be Prologues to Crowns and Immortality, but ſuch who followed deſerted Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as the people our Saviour into the Wilderneſs for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44746:21"/>the miracle of Loaves, ſeeking worldly advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,, might pawn their ſouls for traſh, and ſin for a morſel of bread.</p>
            <p>It is an Atheiſtical piece of folly to diſown Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, that we may gratifie weak Surmiſers.</p>
            <p>The cuſtom of ſwearing and forſwearing had in our unhappy Land took away the ſenſe of perjury: by the no infrequent uſe of Poyſon it went into the opinion of ſuch nutriment as might ſeem neceſſary for their conſtitutions. In a wilderneſs of Apes and Monkeys none could dread by an Oath to take in a Spider.</p>
            <p>That Oaths may make a Land mourn, we have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to aſſure, and reaſon to inſtruct us: but how they can be the inſtruments to our rejoycing, may be an Article of that Creed only which could exchange a Chriſt for an <hi>Adonis,</hi> and make Religion truckle to every darling folly.</p>
            <p>In ſuch an Apoſtacie as might make an unhappy Land ſigh, and wonder at her ſelf ſo ſoon turn'd Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; Some believe a thundring Legion to have ſecur'd our <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> we received a <hi>Charles</hi> by the grace of God, not favour of Men. No quirks nor intrigues of giddie Polititians, but he alone who rules the wheel of human viciſſitudes, produc'd this happyer Revolution; the beſt of Phyſitians, and no worm'd-brain'd Mountebank of State, ſubven'd to our diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; when the twiſting of ſand by fooliſh combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations was found a ſucceſleſs folly, and the brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44746:22"/>hopes of fondeſt Royaliſts might paſs for phrenzy. God derided from heaven, and by dividing their Councils, who were enemies to our <hi>David</hi> turn'd the wiſdom of our <hi>Achitophels</hi> into a Rope.</p>
            <p>When the Bricks were doubled a <hi>Moſes</hi> came: our Task-maſters grown intolerable, God raiſ'd us up Deliverers. The Stars in their courſes, which ſought againſt, fight for us: the moſt inauſpicious Planets by happier conjunctions, depoſit their male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence, and ſeem to have friendly aſpects for Loyalty by a more propitious revolution. Sure this was the Lords doing, and ſhould be marvellous in our eyes. God ſcatter'd the men who took delight in war, and by a bloodleſs victory gave us peace: the prayers and tears of a poor and diſtreſſed party, the weapons of the Church militant, prevail'd over the loud cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blaſphemy and perjuries of their Enemies.</p>
            <p>The war begun from <hi>Scotland,</hi> a Nation fatal to Princes, a Region of darkneſs can give light, and the North infamous for ill, muſt be celebrated for good, ſince from that place, we receiv'd the firſt part of for cure, to which weow'd the beginning of miſchief.</p>
            <p>The Lord, who being a General, gave way to a Princes ruine, without which it could not have been effected, now a private man opens a way for a General which led for a King's Reſtauration, without which it might have been vainly hoped.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:44746:22"/>
            <p>The Dragons tayl, which gave Royalty the fatal wound, cures it by an Antimonarchical vote; by ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to introduce a plurality of Generals, brings in one King.</p>
            <p>The Members which an Army ſecluded, an Army reſtores. Now better reſtored to their ſenſes then to believe a King (though intitl'd to the name of a <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) when he call'd them all Princes: they could not now fancy the Members Eternal (who by the loſs of that unhappy head, which intruſted with power for its own ruine, might find themſelves mortal:) they could no longer dream of being Omnipotent, when as a debt due to vengeance for denying the juſt tribute of Allegiance, they had encountred the curſe of curſes, been ſervants of ſervants, and what might be the higheſt aggravation, enſlaved by their own vaſſals.</p>
            <p>An Anteſignane of Schiſm ſeems a Precurſor of Loyalty; he, who by impoſing on factious ears had juſtly loſt his own, now might ſeem worthy of the reſerv'd head, which in its lucid intervals could be ſo beneficially ſober.</p>
            <p>Loyal Reaſon was ſuch a miracle from the ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting Author, as could produce a ſelf-denying Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, which might be as inſtrumental to a happy Reſtauration, as that was to the utter extinguiſhing of faint and glimmering Loyalty.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:44746:23"/>
            <p>The <hi>Sampſons,</hi> who had been bound and blinded by deceitful <hi>Dalilahs,</hi> falſe Oaths, and fooliſh Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, though with their own diſſolution can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to pluck down the houſe of the Philiſtians ſo long devoted to the Idols folly.</p>
            <p>A ſober Council met; the heart of the Kingdom votes for an Head, that it might be no longer a ſenſleſs Nation: By whoſe return'd command a loyal Body is legally ſummon'd, which may truly hear Patriots, Reſtorers, an healing Senate, Sanctuaries, not ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-houſes of Innocents, who by contributing religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and loyal votes have expiated there the cruel follies, where irreligious and diſloyal ſuffrages chang'd an happy Land into a field of blood.</p>
            <p>The merry Dr. <hi>Collins</hi> deſir'd his taking of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant might be deferr'd till the day of Judgment, when it would be clearly known what became of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters.</p>
            <p>Wiſe men will ſuſpend raſh cenſures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> While the Curtain is drawn the beſt of Prophets are but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Conjecturers.</p>
            <p>Nothing of earthly glory hath been wanting to grace our <hi>Heroe,</hi> ev'n to the <hi>Apotheoſis</hi> of an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:44746:23"/>
            <p>Our Patron <hi>George</hi> interr'd, a ſolemnity was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a Tutelar Saint of the name, which had it been perform'd, an hot-brain'd Zealot, who had peruſ'd a <hi>Tertullian,</hi> or a St. <hi>Cyprian de ſpectaculis,</hi> might be more dangerouſly troubleſom to the diſcompoſure of weak and ſcrupulous noddles, then the Polypragmatick Lawyer in his leſs ſignificant, and more ridiculous miſquoting of them againſt Stage-plays. That which is not evil in it ſelf may be ſometimes not well adviſ'd.</p>
            <p>The order of the Garter may defend it ſelf by its Motto, <hi>Evil to him who evil thinketh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theognis</hi> will have <hi>Jupiter</hi> neither with rain nor without it to pleaſe all men. Neither a cloſe fiſt nor an open hand can want a miſconſtruction: What was wanting to neareſt Relations, was conferr'd on the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, without whom all might ſeem unavailable for a Crown.</p>
            <p>Wiſe men can be pleaſ'd with the moſt excellent gratitude, and fools can be gratifi'd with the gayetie of the ſight.</p>
            <p>It was the cuſtom of Heathens to deſtroy the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving under pretence of honouring the Dead; not a few made cloſe mourners by a civil death, ſeem'd to follow the corps of an Uſurper.</p>
            <p>Some can fancy that an <hi>Eſſex, Ireton,</hi> and a <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> lay in their beds of blaſphem'd honour with more
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:44746:24"/>fond State: None are ſuppoſ'd to have equall'd his funeral Pomp inferior alone to that of Princes by a Diadem: The defects of earth may heaven ſupply, by changing a fickle Coronet into a never fading Crown.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mars</hi> in moſt opinions is beſt pictur'd reaking in blood. A General render'd inglorious, if not expoſ'd in the purple of War: To bring in our <hi>Heroe</hi> with the white Robes of a Confeſſor, and diſingag'd from the bloody Camps of a rebellious Schiſm to make a Souldier of the Church Militant, which can only lead to the truly triumphant paths of Glory, if an errour is more venial then by intitling to the craſt to beſtow on him the prey of Foxes; a great rather then good renown, unworthy of a Chriſtian Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, Let <hi>Mahometans</hi> glory in praiſes common to Wolves, Bears and Tygers, who expect in Paradiſe no pleaſure above thoſe of Goats, by the enjoyment of brutiſh ſenſuality.</p>
            <p>Fooliſh Hiſtorians, like fond Heraulds, make the moſt ſavage of Beaſts ſupporters to the Arms of the higheſt Grandeur, butcheries and debaucheries the prime parts in the tragedies of their Heroes; what but nam'd might turn Chriſtians blood into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geal'd cake of Ice, is affix'd to the ſtory to make a more horrible <hi>Polyphemus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcretion ſhould lay aſide the bloody Shirt: The fam'd Conquerour of the Eaſt, who inſtead of all the vain pomp of proud funerals, would have a Shirt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:44746:24"/>carried aloft, in triumph to ſhow how ſmall a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was left a <hi>Saladine</hi> after his mighty acquiſitions, ſurely had a cleanly ſhift, and no bloody emblem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ'd of humane inconſtancie. The cruel piece of duty, which ſacrific'd a man to revenge for an injur'd Father, though ſome can fancy generous, heroick, and a prophetick action which firſt made the Souldier who was to reſtore the common Parent, may it ever be forgot, whilſt the bloodleſs conqueſt for a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys Father never wants a grateful Commemoration.</p>
            <p>May the bloody Atchievements in a Belgick, Iriſh, Scottiſh War be ever ſilenc'd, and after ſo honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a death be introduc'd by no puny Hiſtorian, who while he fancies the erecting of Trophies, by accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the dangerouſly acquir'd conqueſts of an <hi>Heroe,</hi> expoſes a brutiſh valour and bafled reaſon, for marks of honour by a miſtake of objects, affixes indelible notes of infamy. While the Lyon is forgot, may the triumphs of the Lamb be celebrated, who unlearn'd us the fierceneſs of Savages, and by attending to the voice of Peace, became a <hi>Gratioſo</hi> to a moſt peaceable Prince on Earth, and hath the promiſe of the bleſſing which attends upon Peace-makers, and thus may be intitled a Favourite to the King of Kings, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains not the title of the Prince of Peace.</p>
            <p>It was no cruel victory to which our <hi>Heroe</hi> ow'd his honours, and three Nations their preſervation. God appear'd not in the thunder and lightning of War, but in the ſoft whiſperings of Peace for the moſt happy of Reſtaurations:</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:44746:25"/>
            <p>The General can never want the Encomium of a <hi>Fabius,</hi> will be ever intitled by delays the Reſtorer: To attribute our Reſtauration to the Churches Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, though an Heterodox, can be no culpable opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which cannot diſhonour God by aſcribing all to his mercies, nor the King to have his cauſe own'd by Heaven, nor the General, by being made an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the hand of the Almighty, when his own Arm was withered by the loſs of ſtrength in a Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>The Pſalmiſts Fool, ſaid in his heart there was no God; and he ſaid that all men were lyers: may Wars, Plagues, nor Fires, be the cruel Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to inſtruct that truth which we are ſo apt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, To God only belongeth ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but to thy Name be the Glory. Who would rob God of his Glory on Earth, may fall ſhort of being glorified in Heaven.</p>
            <closer>To God alone as ever due, be ever Glory, whoſe Fame only can make an Hiſtory Everlaſting.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3 <hi>read</hi> Heroe, <hi>Onogyros,</hi> inamelling. P. 4. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> out of. <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>r.</hi> cauſe. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 12. not the <hi>p,</hi> 18. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>omit</hi> to. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>r.</hi> go to. <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>r. M.</hi> his caſe. <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>r.</hi> rolls <hi>for</hi> roots. <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>for</hi> place <hi>r.</hi> peace. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>r.</hi> predeſtinarian. <hi>p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 12. lick'd. <hi>p.</hi> 35. 2. <hi>r.</hi> a <hi>for</hi> its. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>leave out</hi> and.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44746:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
